Guys, we have an issue.
رفاق، لدينا قضية
(Laughter)
(ضحك الحضور)
Growth is fading away, and it's a big deal.
النمو يتضاءل تدريجيًا وهذه معضلة كبيرة
Our global economy stops growing.
اقتصادنا العالمي توقف عن النمو
And it's not new.
وهذا ليس بجديد
Growth has actually declined for the last 50 years.
النمو في الواقع بانخفاض خلال الخمسين سنة الفائتة
If we continue like this, we need to learn
إذا استمررنا هكذا ، نحن بحاجة لتعلم
how to live in a world with no growth in the next decade.
كيف نعيش في عالم بدون نمو في العقد القادم
This is scary because when the economy doesn't grow,
هذا مخيف لأنه عندما لا ينمو الاقتصاد
our children don't get better lives.
أبناءنا لن يحصلوا على معيشة أفضل
What's even scarier is that when the pie does not grow,
الأكثر إخافة من ذلك هي عندما لا تنمو الكعكة
each of us get a smaller piece.
كل شخص منا سيحصل على قطعة أصغر
We're then ready to fight for a bigger one.
عندها سنستعد للقتال من أجل القطعة الأكبر
This creates tensions and serious conflicts.
هذا سيخلق توتر وصراعات خطيرة
Growth matters a lot.
النمو في غاية الأهمية
If we look at the history of growth,
عندما نلقي نظرة على تاريخ النمو
times of big growth have always been fueled
أوقات النمو الكبيرة دائمًا ما كانت تُدعم
by big manufacturing revolutions.
عن طريق الثورات التصنيعية الكبيرة
It happened three times, every 50-60 years.
حدثت ثلاث مرات كل 50-60 عام
The steam engine in the middle of the 19th century,
المحرك البخاري في منتصف القرن التاسع عشر
the mass-production model in the beginning of the 20th century --
نموذج إنتاج المادة في بداية القرن العشرين
thanks, Mr. Ford.
الشكر للسيد فورد
And the first automation wave in the 1970s.
والموجة الآلية الأولى في السبعينيات
Why did these manufacturing revolutions
لماذا هذه الثورات التصنيعية
create huge growth in our economies?
خلقت نمو هائل في اقتصاداتنا؟
Because they have injected huge productivity improvement.
لأنها ضخت تحسينات إنتاجية ضخمة
It's rather simple:
إنها بسيطة إلى حد ما
in order to grow, you need to be producing more,
من أجل أن تنمو، عليك أن تكون منتج أكثر
putting more into our economy.
تضخ أكثر في اقتصادنا
This means either more labor or more capital or more productivity.
هذا يعني إما المزيد من العمل أو المزيد من رأس المال أو إنتاجية أكثر
Each time, productivity has been the growth lever.
بكل مرة الإنتاجية تكون رافعة للنمو
I'm here today to tell you
أنا هنا اليوم لأخبركم
that we are on the verge of another huge change,
بأننا على وشك تغيير ضخم آخر
and that this change, surprisingly enough,
وأن هذا التغيير المدهش بما فيه الكفاية
is going to come from manufacturing, again.
سوف يأتي من التصنيع مرة أخرى
It will get us out of our growth slump
وسوف يخرجنا من الركود بالنمو
and it will change radically the way globalization has been shaped
وسيحدث تغييرًا جذريًا بشكل العولمة التي تشكلت من قبل
over the last decade.
في العقد الماضي
I'm here to tell you about the amazing fourth manufacturing revolution
أنا هنا لأخبركم عن ثورة التصنيع الرابعة المذهلة
that is currently underway.
والتي هي قيد التنفيذ الآن
It's not as if we've done nothing with manufacturing
الأمر ليس كأننا لم نفعل شيء في التصنيع
since the last revolution.
خلال الفترة الماضية
Actually, we've made some pretty lame attempts
في الواقع، لقد فعلنا بعض المحاولات الضعيفة
to try to revitalize it.
لمحاولة تنشيطها
But none of them have been the big overhaul
لكن لم تحقق إحداهم تغييرًا كبيرًا
we really need to get us growing again.
نحن بحاجة فعلاً للنمو من جديد
For example, we've tried to relocate our factories offshore
على سبيل المثال، لقد حاولنا أن ننقل مصانعنا للخارج
in order to reduce cost and take advantage of cheap labor.
من أجل خفض التكاليف والاستفادة من العمالة الرخيصة
Not only did this not inspire productivity,
لم يكتفِ هذا الأمر بعدم إحياء الإنتاجية
but it only saved money for a short period of time,
ولكنه فقط وفر المال لفترة قصيرة من الزمن
because cheap labor didn't stay cheap for long.
لأن العمالة الرخيصة لم تبق رخيصة لفترة طويلة
Then, we've tried to make our factories larger
وبعدها حاولنا لجعل مصانعنا أكبر
and we specialized them by product.
وخصصناها حسب المنتج
The idea was that we can make a lot of one product
كانت الفكرة بأننا بإمكاننا تصنيع الكثير من منتج واحد
and stockpile it to be sold with demand.
ويتم تخزينه ليتم بيعه مع الطلب
This did help productivity for a while.
وهذا لم يساعد الإنتاج لفترة وجيزة
But it introduced a lot of rigidities in our supply chain.
ولكنه أدخل الكثير من الجمود في سلسلة التوريد لدينا
Let's take fashion retail.
دعونا نأخذ تجارة الأزياء
Traditional clothing companies
شركات الملابس التقليدية
have built offshore, global, rigid supply chains.
قامت ببناء سلاسل توريد صلبة خارجية وعالمية
When fast-fashion competitors like Zara
عندما قاموا منافسي الأزياء مثل زارا
started replenishing their stocks faster
بالبدء بتزويد المخزونات بشكل أسرع
from two collections a year to one collection a month,
من مجموعتين في السنة لمجموعة واحدة في الشهر
none of them have been able to keep up with the pace.
لم يكونوا قادرين بمواكبة هذه الوتيرة
Most of them are in great difficulties today.
معظمهم في صعوبات كبيرة اليوم
Yet, with all of their shortcomings,
ومع هذا، مع كل أوجه القصور لديها
those are the factories we know today.
تلك هي المصانع التي نعرفها اليوم
When you open the doors,
عندما تفتح الأبواب
they look the same as they did 50 years ago.
تبدو هي نفسها كما كانت عليه قبل 50 عام
We've just changed the location, the size, the way they operate.
لقد غيرت فقط المكان والحجم والطريقة التي يعملون بها
Can you name anything else that looks the same
هل بالإمكان تسمية أي شيء آخر يبدو هو نفسه
as it did 50 years ago?
قبل 50 عام؟
It's crazy.
أنه جنون
We've made all the tweaks to the model that we could,
لقد فعلنا جميع التحويلات للنموذج
and now we hit its limits.
والآن نصطدم بحدوده
After all of our attempts to fix the manufacturing model failed,
بعد كل محاولاتنا لإصلاح فشل نموذج التصنيع
we thought growth could come from elsewhere.
كنا نعتقد بأن النمو ممكن أن يتحقق من مكان آخر
We turned to the tech sector --
تحولنا إلى قطاع التكنولوجيا
there's been quite a lot of innovations there.
كان هناك الكثير جدًا من الابتكارات
Just to name one: the Internet.
فقط لذكر إحداهم: الإنترنت
We hoped it could produce growth.
لقد أملنا بأنها قد تحقق النمو
And indeed, it changed our lives.
وبالفعل، لقد غيرت حياتنا
It made big waves in the media, the service, the entertainment spaces.
وخلقت موجات كبيرة في وسائل الإعلام والخدمة ومساحات الترفيه
But it hasn't done much for productivity.
ولكنها لم تحقق الكثير للإنتاجية
Actually, what's surprising is that productivity is on the decline
في الواقع، ما يثير الدهشة هو أن الإنتاجية بانخفاض
despite all of those innovation efforts.
على الرغم من جميع تلك الجهود الابتكارية
Imagine that -- sitting at work, scrolling through Facebook,
تخيل ذلك، الجلوس بالمكتب وتصفح فيس بوك
watching videos on YouTube has made us less productive.
ومشاهدة مقاطع الفيديو في اليوتيوب جعلنا بإنتاجية أقل
Weird.
يا للغرابه
(Laughter)
(ضحك الجمهور)
This is why we are not growing.
هذا السبب بأننا لم ننمو
We failed at reinventing the manufacturing space,
لقد فشلنا بالتجديد في مساحة التصنيع
and large technological innovations have played away from it.
والابتكارات التكنولوجية الكبيرة كانت بعيده عن ذلك
But what if we could combine those forces?
ولكن ماذا لو استطعنا الجمع بين هذه القوى؟
What if the existing manufacturing and large technological innovation
ماذا لو كان التصنيع الحالي والابتكارات التكنولوجية الكبيرة
came together to create the next big manufacturing reinvention.
جاءت معًا لصنع التجديد التصنيعي الكبير القادم
Bingo!
تمامًا!
This is the fourth manufacturing revolution,
هذه هي ثورة التصنيع الرابعة
and it's happening right now.
وهي تحدث حاليًا
Major technologies are entering the manufacturing space,
التكنولوجيات الرئيسية تدخل مجال التصنيع
big time.
لحظة عظيمة
They will boost industrial productivity by more than a third.
سوف تعزز الإنتاجية لأكثر من الثلث
This is massive, and it will do a lot in creating growth.
هذا شئ ضخم، وستفعل الكثير لتحقيق النمو
Let me tell you about some of them.
دعوني أخبركم بعضها
Have you already met advanced manufacturing robots?
هل التقيتم فعلاً بروبوتات التصنيع المتقدمة؟
They are the size of humans,
إنها بحجم البشر
they actually collaborate with them,
وهي تتعاون في الواقع معهم
and they can be programmed
وبالإمكان برمجتها
in order to perform complex, non-repetitive tasks.
من أجل أداء المهام المعقدة الغير متكررة
Today in our factories, only 8 percent of the tasks are automated.
اليوم في مصانعنا ، فقط 8% من المهام تعتبر أوتوماتيكية
The less complex, the more repetitive ones.
الأقل تعقيدًا هم الأكثر تكرارًا
It will be 25 percent in 10 years.
سوف تكون بنسبة 25% خلال 10 سنوات
It means that by 2025,
هذا يعني أنه بحلول عام 2025
advanced robots will complement workers
الروبوتات المتطورة ستكون مكملة للعمال
to be, together, 20 percent more productive,
ليكونا معًا أكثر إنتاجية بنسبة 20%
to manufacture 20 percent more outputs,
لتصنيع منتجات أعلى بنسبة 20%
to achieve 20 percent additional growth.
ولتحقيق نمو إضافي بنسبة 20%
This isn't some fancy, futuristic idea.
هذا الأمر ليس مجرد خيال وفكرة مستقبلية
These robots are working for us right now.
هذه الروبوتات تعمل لدينا في الوقت الحالي
Last year in the US, they helped Amazon prepare and ship all the products
في العام الماضي، ساعدت الروبوتات أمازون بتحضير وشحن جميع المنتجات
required for Cyber Monday,
المطلوبة لـ "الأثنين الإلكتروني"
the annual peak of online retail.
وهو أعلى يوم في السنة في التجارة بالإنترنت
Last year in the US,
في العام الماضي بالولايات المتحدة
it was the biggest online shopping day of the year and of history.
كان أكبر يوم للتسوق بالإنترنت في السنة وفي التاريخ
Consumers spent 3 billion dollars on electronics that day.
أنفق المستهلكون 3 مليارات دولار على الإلكترونيات في ذلك اليوم
That's real economic growth.
هذا هو النمو الاقتصادي الحقيقي
Then there's additive manufacturing, 3D printing.
ومن ثم هنالك التصنيع الإضافي والطباعة ثلاثية الأبعاد
3D printing has already improved plastic manufacturing
الطباعة ثلاثية الأبعاد قد حسنت بالفعل صناعة البلاستيك
and it's now making its way through metal.
وهي الآن تشق طريقها للمعادن
Those are not small industries.
هذه ليست صناعات صغيرة
Plastic and metals represent 25 percent
البلاستيك والمعادن تمثل نسبة 25%
of global manufacturing production.
من الإنتاج التصنيعي العالمي
Let's take a real example.
دعونا نأخذ مثال حقيقي
In the aerospace industry,
في صناعة الطيران
fuel nozzles are some of the most complex parts to manufacture,
فوهات الوقود تعتبر واحدة من أكثر الأجزاء تعقيدًا في تصنيعها
for one reason:
لسبب واحد
they are made up of 20 different parts
تتكون هي من 20 قطعة مختلفة
that need to be separately produced
تحتاج أن تُنتج منفصله
and then painstakingly assembled.
ومن ثم تجميعها بشق الأنفس
Aerospace companies are now using 3D printing,
شركات الطيران تستخدم الآن الطباعة ثلاثية الأبعاد
which allows them to turn those 20 different parts
مما يسمح لهم بتحويل تلك العشرون قطعة
into just one.
إلى قطعة واحدة
The results?
النتائج؟
40 percent more productivity,
إنتاجية أكبر بنسبة 40%
40 percent more output produced, 40 percent more growth
40% كمية منتجة أكثر و40% نمو أكبر
for this specific industry.
لهذه الصناعة بالتحديد
But actually, the most exciting part of this new manufacturing revolution
ولكن في الواقع، الجزء الأكثر إثارة في هذه الثورة التصنيعية الجديدة
goes much beyond productivity.
يذهب إلى من وراء الإنتاجية
It's about producing better, smarter products.
إنه بشأن إنتاج أفضل ومنتجات أكثر ذكاءًا
It's about scale customization.
وبشأن نطاق التخصيص
Imagine a world where you can buy the exact products you want
تخيل عالمًا حيث بإمكانك شراء المنتجات التي تريدها بالضبط
with the functionalities you need,
مع الوظائف التي تريدها
with the design you want,
والتصميم الذي تريده
with the same cost and lead time
بنفس التكلفة وفترة التصنيع
as a product that's been mass produced,
لمنتج تم تصنيعه بكميات كبيرة
like your car, or your clothes or your cell phone.
مثل سيارتك أو ملابسك أو هاتفك الخلوي
The new manufacturing revolution makes it possible.
الثورة التصنيعية الجديدة جعلتها بالإمكان
Advanced robots can be programmed
الروبوتات المتطورة من الممكن برمجتها
in order to perform any product configuration
من أجل أداء أي ترتيبات للمنتج
without any setup time or ramp up.
بدون أي وقت للإعدادات أو التشويش
3D printers instantaneously produce any customized design.
الطابعات ثلاثية الأبعاد تنتج على الفور أي تصميم حسب الطلب
We are now able to produce a batch of one product, your product,
نحن الآن بإمكاننا إنتاج كمية من منتج واحد، المنتج الخاص بك
at the same cost and lead time as a batch of many.
بنفس التكلفة وفترة التصنيع لكميات كبيرة
Those are only a few examples of the manufacturing revolution at play.
تلك ليست سوى أمثلة بسيطة من ثورة التصنيع
Not only will manufacturing become more productive,
ليس فقط التصنيع سوف يكون بإنتاجية أكبر
it will also become more flexible,
سيصبح أيضًا أكثر مرونة
and those were exactly the elements of growth that we are missing.
وتلك بالتحديد هي عناصر النمو التي افتقدناها
But actually, there are even some bigger implications
ولكن في الواقع، يوجد أيضًا بعض الأثار الكبيرة
for all of us when manufacturing will find its way back into the limelight.
بالنسبة لنا عندما يجد التصنيع طريقه مرة أخرى إلى الأضواء
It will create a huge macroeconomic shift.
سوف ينشئ تحول اقتصادي ضخم
First, our factories will be relocated into our home markets.
أولاً، المصانع سوف تُنقل إلى الأسواق المحلية
In the world of scale customization,
في عالم نطاق التخصيص
consumer proximity is the new norm.
قرب المستهلك هو المعيار الجديد
Then, our factories will be smaller, agile.
ومن ثم، مصانعنا ستكون أصغر حجمًا وأخف
Scale does not matter anymore, flexibility does.
التدرج لن يهم بعد الآن المرونة هي ما تهم
They will be operating on a multi-product, made-to-order basis.
سوف تعمل على منتجات متعددة، وعلى أساس الإنتاج حسب الطلب
The change will be drastic.
التغيير سوف يكون جذريًا
Globalization will enter a new era.
العولمة ستدخل عهدًا جديدًا
The East-to-West trade flows
إنتاجات التجارة بين الشرق والغرب
will be replaced by regional trade flows.
ستستبدل بإنتاجات تجارة إقليمية
East for East, West for West.
الشرق للشرق، والغرب للغرب
When you think about that,
عندما تفكر بهذا الأمر
the old model was pretty much insane.
النموذج القديم كان مجنونًا إلى حد كبير
Piling up stocks, making products travel the whole world
تراكم المخزونات، صنع منتجات تسافر حول العالم
before they reach their end consumers.
قبل أن تصل إلى المستهلكين النهائيين
The new model, producing just next to the consumer market,
أما النموذج الجديد، الصنع بجوار سوق المستهلك
will be much cleaner, much better for our environment.
سيكون أكثر نظافة وأفضل بكثير للبيئة
In mature economies, manufacturing will be back home,
في الاقتصادات الناضجة، سيعود التصنيع للوطن
creating more employment,
وسيخلق مزيد من فرص العمل
more productivity and more growth.
إنتاجية أكبر ونمو أكبر
Good news, isn't it?
أخبار جيدة، أليست كذلك؟
But here's the thing with growth --
ولكن بخصوص النمو
it does not come automatically.
إنه لا يأتي تلقائيًا
Mature economies will have to seize it.
الاقتصادات الناضجة عليها أن تغتنمه
We'll have to massively re-train our workforce.
علينا تكثيف إعادة تدريب القوى العاملة لدينا
In most countries, like in my country, France,
في معظم الدول، كما هو الحال في بلدي فرنسا
we've told our children that manufacturing had no future.
لقد أخبرنا أطفالنا بأن التصنيع لا مستقبل له
That it was something happening far away.
هذا كان أمرًا يحدث بشكل بعيد
We need to reverse that
علينا أن نعكس ذلك
and teach manufacturing again at university.
ونعيد تدريس التصنيع في الجامعة
Only the countries that will boldly transform
فقط في البلدان التي ستتحول بجرأة
will be able to seize this growth.
ستكون قادره على انتهاز هذا النمو
It's also a chance for developing economies.
كما أنها ستكون فرصة للاقتصادات النامية
Of course China and other emerging economies
بالطبع الصين والاقتصادات الناشئة الأخرى
won't be the factory of the world anymore.
لن تكون مصنع العالم بعد الآن
Actually, it was not a sustainable model in the long term,
في الواقع، لم يكن نموذج قادر على المواصلة على المدى البعيد
as those countries are becoming richer.
لأن هذه الدول أصبحت أكثر ثراء
Last year, it was already as expensive to produce in Brazil
في العام الماضي، كان الإنتاج مكلف في البرازيل
as to produce in France.
كما هو مكلف في فرنسا
By 2018, manufacturing costs in China will be on par with the US.
بحلول عام 2018، تكاليف التصنيع في الصين ستكون مساوية للولايات المتحدة
The new manufacturing revolution
ثورة التصنيع الجديدة
will accelerate the transition of those emerging economies
سوف تسرع عملية الإنتقال لتلك الاقتصادات الناشئة
towards a model driven by domestic consumption.
إلى نموذج مرتبط بالاستهلاك المحلي
And this is good,
وهذا أمر جيد
because this is where growth will be created.
لأنه بهذا النموذج سيتكون النمو
In the next five years,
في الخمس سنوات المقبلة
the next billion consumers in China will inject more growth in our economies
المليار مستهلك المقبل في الصين سيضخون المزيد من النمو في اقتصاداتنا
than the top five European markets together.
أكبر من الأسواق الخمسة الكبرى في أوروبا معًا
This fourth manufacturing revolution is a chance for all of us.
ثورة التصنيع الرابعة هي فرصة لنا جميعًا
If we play it right,
إذا لعبناها بشكل صحيح
we'll see sustainable growth in all of our economies.
سنرى نمو ثابت في جميع اقتصاداتنا
This means more wealth distributed to all of us
وهذا يعني مزيد من الثروة ستوزع علينا جميعًا
and a better future for our children.
ومستقبل أفضل لأبناءنا
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم